Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is being pre-recorded. Today's
דף daf is דף ו' Daf Vav in order to be able
to participate in the festivities for tomorrow for יום העצמאות. Yom Ha'atzmaut.
We pick up in the middle of דף ה' עמוד ב', Daf
Hey Amud Bet, line that starts with the word מותרה. mosarah. We're
in the issue about how do you know the reality that ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish points out about the somewhat bizarre nature that an
אשם asham which normally is connected to the בעלים, ba'alim, to the
owners, how can it be brought without being connected to the owners?
And if it's שחוטה shechted שלא לשמה, shelo lishmah, לשמה, lishmah,
and the גמרא Gemara basically says you have some form of that,
that a חטאת, chatas, even if the owners die, it gets reincarnated
as an עולה, olah, the money gets transferred. Now the גמרא Gemara
says by excuse me, an אשם, asham, an אשם asham even if
the owners die, it gets reincarnated and gets brought as an עולה.
olah. So an אשם asham at least you can have some form
in which it is brought not connected to the owners. That's why
an אשם asham that was
שחוטה shechted שלא לשמה shelo lishmah could be brought even though it's
not connected to the owners. Now חטאת, chatas, אף על גב דקריס
af al gav d'karis מותרה, mosarah, the line starts with the word
מותרה mosarah about halfway down ה' עמוד ב'. Hey Amud Bet.
Even though you do have something similar if somebody separated out two
animals to be a חטאת, chatas, one to be a backup for
the other, and therefore the second one could be brought, although that's
much a different, a very different case, so anyway maybe you might
think that a חטאת chatas also could therefore have the possibility of
being brought even though it's not connected to the owners. So the
גמרא Gemara says maybe, maybe in theory that phenomenon is somehow possible
by a חטאת. chatas. We're not saying that's an impossible phenomenon although
it's extremely rare. But nevertheless מיעט רחמנא היא, mi'et rachmana hee, it
says חטאת היא. chatas hee. So only done right, only done this
way, only done in the way that it's meant to be done
and connected to the owners does it count as a חטאת. chatas.
So an אשם asham and a חטאת, chatas, more of an אשם
asham can have this reality of not being connected to the owners,
and there's no פסוק pasuk to limit it, and therefore we can
accept the idea שלא לשמה shelo lishmah by an אשם, asham, it
works and it's not connected to the owners. But a חטאת, chatas,
both the phenomenon is almost non-existent and B, the word היא hee
basically says it has to be done exactly this way. So now
the גמרא Gemara is going to say one minute, we have a
word similar to that by an אשם. asham. So the גמרא Gemara
says אשם נמי כתיב ביה הוא, asham nami ksiv bei hu, it
says אשם הוא, asham hu, so maybe only done the right way
is כשר. kosher. No. הוא לאחר הקטרת אימורים הוא דכתיב, Hu le'achar
haktaras emurim hu d'ksiv, there it says אשם הוא, asham hu, it's
the פסוק pasuk speaks about it as after the אימורים emurim were
burnt on the מזבח. mizbeiach. And therefore it says והקטירו המזבח אשה
לה' אשם הוא. v'hiktiru hamizbeiach isheh lashem asham hu. And since אשם
הוא asham hu happens after the אימורים emurim are burnt on the
מזבח, mizbeiach, so that it can't be saying that if it's done
in a wrong way it's invalid because the הוא hu because even
if you didn't do at that stage there's nothing that can invalidate
the קרבן, korban, you know, even before the אימורים, emurim, the קרבן
korban is done. So the גמרא Gemara says דכתיב כדתניא d'ksiv kedetanya
like
we תניא tania ברייתא. b'raisa. אבל אשם לא נאמר בו הוא אלא
אחר הקטרת אימורים, aval asham lo ne'emar bo hu ela achar haktaras
emurim, ועצמו אם לא הקטיר אימורים כשר, v'atzmo im lo hiktir emurim
kasher, and if you didn't bring the אימורים emurim for an אשם
asham it's כשר. kasher. So since we're at a stage where you're
not going to be able to affect the כשרות kashrus of a
קרבן, korban, the הוא hu there cannot be telling you if it's
done שלא לשמה. shelo lishmah. So at this stage what we've basically
answered ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, the phenomenon of an אשם asham not
totally connected to the owners אחר מיתה achar misa whatever is possible
and therefore when it's שלא לשמה shelo lishmah it can work without
working for the owners. And even though it says אשם הוא, asham
hu, that's not talking about this, that's something that refers to אחר
הקטרת אימורים. achar haktaras emurim. So now of course the גמרא's Gemara
question is so what is that הוא hu referring to? ואלא הוא
למה לי, V'ela hu lama li, so what is the הוא hu
doing? לדרב הונא אמר רב, Lid'Rav Huna amar Rav, דאמר רב הונא
אמר
רב אשם שניתק לרעייה
D'amar Rav Huna amar Rav asham
shenitak l're'iyah if שחטו סתם כשר. shechto stam kasher. So an אשם,
asham, exactly אשם asham that the owners died and what do you
do? You're going to wait for it to get a מום mum
and then you're going to redeem the money and use the money
to buy an עולה. olah. Now since the קדושה kedusha is ultimately
going to be transferred for an עולה, olah, והלכה היא v'halacha hi
that at a certain stage if you accidentally or
improperly שחוטה shechted it even without redeeming the money using the money
to buy an עולה olah because that's where it's headed it actually
works as an עולה. olah. What is that stage? So רב הונא
Rav Huna says in the name of רב, Rav, דאמר רב הונא
אמר רב, d'amar Rav Huna amar Rav, excuse me, רב הונא Rav
Huna says in the name of רב Rav that it is when
it is put out to pasture. If it's put out to pasture
with and you're going to wait till it gets a blemish, so
it's in the process of being transferred to the קדושה kedusha of
an עולה olah once it gets a blemish and now you שחוטה
shechted it before the blemish it actually is going to work as
an עולה. olah. ושחטו סתם U'shchato stam so כשר. kasher. And even
if you שחוטה shechted it not as an עולה olah since that's
where it's headed it's defined as an עולה. olah. Okay that's as
opposed to saying that you have to have כוונה kavana that it
works as an עולה olah right now. וניתק אין, V'nitak in, now
even there it's only once it's been put out to pasture, לא
ניתק לא lo nitak lo but not if it hasn't. מאי טעמא
Mai ta'ama what's the reasoning? אמר קרא הוא בהוויתו יהא. Amar kra
hu b'hayavto yehei. So the הוא hu says that there's stickiness to
the אשם asham status. It sticks and it doesn't go away so
easily. Okay, to me, still, putting it out to pasture is pretty
easily that it's now redefined its identity. You haven't even transferred the
money, it doesn't even have a מום, mum, you haven't even intentionally
שחט shechted it for something else, but anyway, it's a certain degree
of stickiness. So that's what the הוא hu is telling you, or
the, excuse me, the הוא, hu, and that's what we learn from
it. But if it's done שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, it's כשר, kosher,
it just doesn't count for the owners. Okay, now moving on. יתיב
רב נחמן ורב ששת ויתיב רב אדא בר מתנא גבייהו, Yativ Rav
Nachman v'Rav Sheshet v'yativ Rav Adda bar Matna gabeihu, Rav Nachman and
Rav Sheshet were sitting and Rav Adda bar Matna was by them,
ויתבי וקאמרי v'yatvi v'ka'amri and they were saying, הא דקאמר רבי אלעזר,
ha d'ka'amar Rabbi Elazar, רבי אלעזר's Rabbi Elazar's response to ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish is, ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, what bothers you with this
phenomenon that it's כשר kosher and it doesn't work for the owners?
That happens every time after somebody dies, at least if you're talking
about an עולה ושלמים, olah u'shlamim, and then the גמרא Gemara focused
on an אשם. asham. לימא ליה ריש לקיש, Leima lei Resh Lakish,
to why doesn't ריש לקיש Resh Lakish say, look, even if we're
talking about an עולה ושלמים olah u'shlamim I have the same problem.
Okay, it's a logical problem. What good does it do me that
you have a precedent? It's still the same logical problem. So why
doesn't ריש לקיש Resh Lakish say back to him, הני נמי לאו
למירצי? hanei nami lav l'mirtzei? Let those also be brought and count
for the owners, like, how do you have, I don't like this
middle phenomenon. Don't tell me you have a precedent לאחר מיתה. le'achar
mita.
So אמר להו רב אדא בר מתנא, amar lehu Rav Adda bar
Matna, Rav Adda bar Matna said, no, that you cannot sort of
try to push that and say let's maybe think that the הלכה
halacha is different, because there's at least one case that it's black
and white that that's the הלכה. halacha. So he says,
יולדת,
אם היא ילדה בניה מי ילדו?
yoledet, im hi yalda b'neha
mi yaldu? Okay, one minute. He says the הלכה halacha is that
if a יולדת yoledet dies and she hasn't brought her עולה, olah,
then her children will bring the עולה. olah. So the idea that
we should argue, hey, why don't we let that work and let
it count and even though the owner is dead and let it
be מרצה? mirtze? So what does it mean מרצה? mirtze? The owner
is already dead. So what should be the הוה אמינא hava amina
that ריש לקיש Resh Lakish should be trying to argue that it
should be מרצה? mirtze? So you could say, if it's an עולה,
olah, if it's a שלמים, shlamim, that somehow it counts on behalf
of the יורשים yorshim who brought it. They get some brownie points
up in heaven. Okay, but now
the
גמרא Gemara is saying, one minute, but that doesn't work in the
context of a יולדת, yoledet, because by a יולדת, yoledet, the קרבן
korban of the עולה olah is about childbirth. It's not about some
type of an atonement for a מצוה, mitzvah, some type of brownie
points. It's part of like a טהרה taharah process around childbirth. And
the sons who are bringing it, let's assume they're sons, they just
didn't, they didn't give birth. So therefore, clearly there's no possibility of
that saying that that should be מרצה. mirtze. So therefore you see
that if you have an idea that the יורשים yorshim can bring
the קרבן, korban, that you cannot argue well let's assume that it's
מרצה mirtze for the יורשים, yorshim, that it somehow gives brownie points
to the יורשים, yorshim, because that's completely irrelevant in the case of
an עולה olah of a יולדת. yoledet. So he says, אמר להו
רב אדא בר מתנא: יולדת, אם היא ילדה בניה מי ילדו? amar
lehu Rav Adda bar Matna: yoledet, im hi yalda b'neha mi yaldu?
So therefore clearly that possibility can't work and again, it's a proof
for this phenomenon of that it's עולה olah not מרצה. mirtze. מתקיף
לה רב אשי, matkif lah Rav Ashi,
one minute, I don't concede the idea that an עולה olah for
a יולדת yoledet does not have some type of an atonement value
and a power. Let's say this woman, like all of us, we
sin, that's why there's יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, that's why you say
והוא רחום יכפר עון, v'hu rachum y'chaper avon, you fall תחנון, Tachnun,
we all sin. So let's say a יולדת, yoledet, when she brings
her עולה olah even though she's bringing it for childbirth, it also
does the function of the atonement of an עולה. olah. What is
the atonement of an עולה? olah? For a מצות עשה mitzvot aseh
that you didn't do. So since it'll work for her even though
it's part of the process of the קרבנות korbanot for childbirth, it'll
work to atone for her מצות עשה. mitzvot aseh. That's part of
the function of that עולה. olah. So the kids could bring it
and it could work for their מצות עשה mitzvot aseh that they
didn't do. So who's to tell you that if she has עשהs
aseh that she hasn't done, לא מכפרא lo mechafra that it doesn't
atone? No, it would work for that. וכיון דכי איכא כמה עשה
גביה מכפרא, v'keivan d'ki ika kama aseh gabei mechafra, and since it
would atone, יורש נמי מכפרא. yoresh nami mechafra. It would also work
for the יורש. yoresh. So again, the argument would be if you
really insist on ריש לקיש's Resh Lakish argument that it should not,
you shouldn't have a middle state and if it's brought then it
should be מכפר, mechaper, then why then the point is why maybe
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish would want to try to push that point
even when יורשים yorshim bring a קרבן? korban? Who says it's not
מכפר, mechaper, not for the dead person, but who says it's not
מכפר mechaper for the יורש yoresh and somehow it has some type
of a positive atonement function or brownie point function as it were
for the יורש? yoresh? Okay, so we don't really have an answer
to that. ריש לקיש Resh Lakish could have maybe pushed his point
even there. But now the גמרא Gemara is going to focus on
this issue of יורש. yoresh. So let's see what it says.
למימרא, l'meimra, says the גמרא, Gemara, this implies that למימרא, l'meimra, I
lost my place. Okay, למימרא דקני להו, l'meimra d'kanya lehu, one minute.
Your idea to suggest that the יורשים Yorshim would get כפרה Kapara
for the קרבן Korban that they're bringing from, you know, their dead
mother means that for them to get כפרה Kapara they have to
own the קרבן. Korban. It's not just their mother's קרבן Korban that
they're bringing, right? Then it wouldn't work for them. Conceptually you think
the mother sanctified an animal, they inherited it, now the same way
they inherit their mother's estate, they now own from a monetary perspective
this קרבן, Korban, which, you know, you could question if that's true,
and that's what you must be assuming if you want to suggest
that they're going to get atonement for the bringing of the קרבן.
Korban. Is that really true? So now we're going to focus on
that question: Do יורשים Yorshim inherit a קרבן? Korban? Are they considered
now the בעלים Ba'alim of the קרבן? Korban? So והאמר רבי יוחנן,
V'ha'amar Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says: הניח מנחה לשני בניו,
Hiniach Mincha lishnei banav, if somebody sanctified a מנחה Mincha and died
and he had two sons and they inherited it. Now the הלכה
Halacha is all the קרבנות Korbanot can be brought בשותפות B'shutfut with
the
exception of a מנחה. Mincha. A מנחה Mincha cannot be brought
בשותפות. B'shutfut. חז"ל Chazal learn it from a פסוק, Pasuk, נפש, Nefesh,
okay, and maybe part of the logic also is that it's such
a poor person's קרבן, Korban, you know, it's so, the Torah is
allowing like, the whole point is that as long as your כוונה
Kavana is לשם שמים, L'shem Shamayim, even a מנחה Mincha can be
brought and be as valuable as an עולה, Olah, as a בהמה
Behemah and so on. But nevertheless, you know, maybe we don't want
even that to be subdivided. Okay, so a מנחה Mincha is the
one thing that cannot be brought in partnership or together with somebody.
So let's say two brothers inherit a מנחה Mincha of their mother
or of their father. Can this מנחה Mincha be brought, or does
it have a status of מנחת שותפים Minchat Shutafim and is not
acceptable? Okay, and that really will point to the question of are
they now considered the owners of this קרבן? Korban? So והאמר רבי
יוחנן, V'ha'amar Rabbi Yochanan, הניח מנחה לשני בניו ומת, Hiniach Mincha lishnei
banav u'met, קריבה, Kreiva, you can bring it, ואין בה משותפות, V'ein
bah mishutfut, it's not considered a קרבן שותפין. Korban Shutafin. So that
seems, ואי סלקא דעתך קניא להו, V'ee salka datchach kanya l'hu, if
they're now the owners and they're the owners of this קרבן, Korban,
נפש אמר רחמנא, Nefesh amar Rachmana, it only says a single soul.
So therefore, ולא קניא להו, V'lo kanya l'hu, and therefore it seems
very clear that they do not own it. And they can bring
it because it's their mother's קרבן Korban or their father's קרבן, Korban,
but they are not the owners. So that seems to be pretty
darn good evidence that when somebody dies, the heirs have to bring
the קרבנות Korbanot that were left over, but they don't own the
קרבן. Korban. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, והאמר רבי יוחנן,
V'ha'amar Rabbi Yochanan, I'm sorry, ולא קניא להו, V'lo kanya l'hu, are
you saying they're not קונה? Koneh? So, I'm sorry, that would have
been read beat me up. אי סלקא דעתך קניא להו נפש אמר
רחמנא. Ee salka datchach kanya l'hu Nefesh amar Rachmana. So it must
be they're not קונה. Koneh. ולא קניא להו, V'lo kanya l'hu, are
they really not קונה? Koneh? והאמר רבי יוחנן, V'ha'amar Rabbi Yochanan, הניח
בהמה לשני בניו ומת. Hiniach behemah lishnei banav u'met. So the same
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that said about the מנחה Mincha that it's
not owned by the two brothers and it's not a מנחת שותפות,
Minchat Shutfut, here he says the following: Let's say somebody left an
animal that was a קרבן, Korban, you know, that hadn't been brought,
and he died and his sons inherited it. קריבה ואין מימיר בה,
Kreiva v'ein mamir bah, you can bring the קרבן Korban and there
will not be a תמורה. Tmura. If one of the sons says
this sanctity is moved from this animal to another, it won't take
effect. Now why won't it take effect? Okay, because the principle is
that a קרבן שותפין Korban Shutafin does not have תמורה. Tmura. So
that seems to be that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying that
this קרבן, Korban, let's say this עולה, Olah, is now owned by
the two brothers and it's an עולת שותפין Olat Shutafin and therefore
it's excluded from תמורה. Tmura. So what you really have is a
contradiction of the two statements of ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. You have
the statement of a מנחה Mincha which says it does not have
the status of מנחת שותפות Minchat Shutfut and therefore can be brought
when it's inherited by two brothers, and you have the עולה Olah
when inherited by two brothers there's no problem of תמורה, Tmura, which
only works if you consider it to be a קרבן שותפין. Korban
Shutafin. Okay, so ריש לקיש Reish Lakish really seems directly to contradict
himself. But the גמרא Gemara is framing it as a question of
are we to infer that the heirs own the קרבן Korban or
don't own the קרבן? Korban? Okay, ואין מימיר בה. V'ein mamir bah.
אי אמרת בשלמא קניא להו, Ee amrat bishlama kanya l'hu, if they
own it, היינו דאין מימיר בה, Hainu d'ein mamir bah, that's why
you can't do תמורה, Tmura, דהוו להו כשותפין, D'havu l'hu k'shutafin, because
then they're like joint owners, ושותפין לא מצו ממירי, V'shutafin lo matzu
mamiri, and joint owners don't have the ability to do תמורה. Tmura.
We learn that out, the whole פרשה Parsha of תמורה Tmura is
said בלשון יחיד. B'lashon yachid. So if שותפין Shutafin own a קרבן,
Korban, no תמורה Tmura takes place. ואי אמרת לא קניא להו, V'ee
amrat lo kanya l'hu, if they don't own it and they're just
bringing their mother's or their father's קרבן Korban like you said by
the מנחה, Mincha, so ממירי נמי למימרי, Mamiri nami l'memrei, they should
have the ability to do תמורה Tmura because it's not now owned
בשותפות. B'shutfut. It's really the mother's קרבן, Korban, nobody owns it or
whatever that they're bringing. הגמרא Ha'Gemara says no. שאני התם דאמר קרא
אם המיר ימיר Shani hatam d'amar kra Im hamir yamir לרבות את
היורש.
L'rabot et
hayoresh. We have one פסוק Pasuk that the double language tells me
that a יורש Yoresh can still do תמורה. Tmura. So what we're
trying to say is fundamentally you don't own it, and that's why
you can bring the מנחה Mincha and it's not a מנחת שותפות,
Minchat Shutfut, and a יורש Yoresh doesn't own it. Okay, but we
know that a יורש Yoresh can do תמורה Tmura by the language
המיר ימיר, Hamir yamir, that he has the ability to do תמורה.
Tmura. ואין שנים ממירין, V'ein shnayim m'mirin, and then
but there's a הלכה Halacha that when there are two you can't
do תמורה. Tmura. So normally that הלכה Halacha means when there are
two
owners you can't. As a יורש yoresh as well, if you're the
only יורש yoresh you can do תמורה. temura. If there's two יורשים
yorshim the same way two joint owners can't do it, two יורשים
yorshim even though you're not owners, right like what we know by
the מנחה Mincha you're not really the owners, you're just a status
of a יורש, yoresh, nevertheless the פסוק pasuk is telling you only
one יורש, yoresh, not two יורשים. yorshim. Okay, so that's what we
have. They're not really the owner, by יורש yoresh you have the
ability to do תמורה temura but not if there are two of
you, okay, even though you're not the owner. Now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: מתקיף לה רב יעקב מנהר פקוד. Matkif lah Rav
Yaakov mi'Nehar Pekod. Rav Yaakov from Nehar Pekod, אלא מעתה ela me'ata
לגבי מעשר דכתיב, lgabei maaser de'chtiv, so let's apply that logic elsewhere,
that if you have two יורשים, yorshim, it doesn't work. Okay, by
מעשר maaser it says ואם גאל יגאל, ve'im gaol yigal, if he
will redeem his מעשר maaser then he adds a fifth, when you
redeem your מעשר שני. maaser sheni. And we say that the double
language is לרבות את היורש, lerabot et hayoresh, to include the heir.
This actually isn't a privilege, this is a sort of penalty, that
the יורש yoresh is considered like the owner and therefore if he
redeems his father's מעשר maaser or, you know, שני, sheni, he has
to add a fifth. Okay, והכא נמי v'hacha nami אחד גואל ואין
שנים גואלים, echad goel v'ein shnayim goalim,
why don't we say the single language גאל יגאל gaol yigal just
means one? And if there are two יורשים yorshim and they inherit
their father's תרומה, teruma, okay, there they really do own it, it's
not like a קרבן, korban, okay, maybe we should say that, you
know,
they don't add a fifth because there are two of them. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, that's not a question. Okay, שאני מעשר
דגבי אבוה נמי איתא בשותפות. shani maaser d'gabei avuha nami ita b'shutfut.
Maaser, even when their father was alive, if you have partners by
מעשר maaser you add a fifth. Okay, so basically what the גמרא
Gemara is saying is the following:
by מעשר maaser there's no problem with being a partner. Partners add
a fifth. So when the יורשים yorshim inherit it, obviously you're not
going to read the פסוק pasuk to say that if two people
genuinely own it in partnership they don't add a fifth, that two
יורשים, yorshim, excuse me one more time.
מעשר, Maaser, there's no principle of שותפות, shutfut, you're considered to be
the full owner and you do add a fifth. I don't know
if I said that right the first time, one more time, מעשר,
maaser, there's no problem of שותפות, shutfut, meaning שותפות shutfut doesn't compromise
the status of being an owner, it doesn't change the הלכה. halacha.
So by מעשר, maaser, if it's owned by שותפות shutfut you add
a fifth like a normal owner, okay, and therefore once the יורש
yoresh doesn't affect
once שותפות shutfut doesn't affect the status of an owner, even in
a normal case of real ownership, it certainly doesn't affect the status
of an owner by the case of the heirs. Okay, so the
heirs also, whether one or two, they're going to add a fifth
the same way a genuine owner, whether one or two, adds a
fifth. So obviously by מעשר, maaser, everybody's anybody who's a part owner,
יורש yoresh or whatever, is adding a fifth because there's never partnership
does not make a difference. But by תמורה temura and by מנחה,
mincha, partnership does make a difference. The הלכות halachot are only said
by single owners and not by partner owners. And what the גמרא
Gemara is saying is, יורשים yorshim are a the יורשים yorshim do
not really own the קרבן, korban, so therefore the מנחה mincha is
not considered a partnership מנחה mincha and it can be brought. Okay,
we talk about partnership ענינים inyanim nowadays. Here's a partnership מנחה, mincha,
it's not a partnership מנחה mincha and it can be brought, okay,
whereas the תמורה, temura, what we learn from the פסוקים psukim is
that even though it isn't genuinely a partnership תמורה temura when inherited
by heirs, but because the תורה Torah recognizes the heirs and there's
a הלכה halacha of partnership, we're going to say that when it's
inherited by heirs who are partners, even though they're not the genuine
owner, it's excluded from the law of תמורה. temura. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara is going to ask about that. Let's take a
look. אמר ליה רב אסי לרב אשי, Amar lei Rav Assi l'Rav
Ashi, so Rav Assi said to Rav Ashi: ומנא? u'mina? From that
I can ask. אי אמרת בשלמא קני להו, I amart bishlama kanei
lehu, היינו דחד ממימר. hainu d'chad memir. So I still it goes
like this: he says if you say that they genuinely own it,
I understand, fine. So now you're saying that you don't own the
קרבן korban that you inherit,
and therefore there's a problem of two people, but nevertheless two heirs
can't do תמורה, temura, one heir can. But one minute. He says
like this: if you really did own it, I would understand why
one person could do תמורה. temura. אלא אי אמרת לא קני להו,
Ela i amart lo kanei lehu, you're trying to argue that heirs
don't really own the קרבן. korban.
So your whole discussion was partners, not partners, one minute. If you
don't own the קרבן, korban, you don't have any right to do
תמורה temura in the first place. You don't have any power to
do תמורה. temura. It's like I tried to do תמורה temura on
your animal. It wouldn't work, okay. אלא אי אמרת לא קני להו,
Ela i amart lo kanei lehu, you don't really own it, היכי
ממימר? heichi memir? How could you do תמורה? temura? ואמר רב ואמר
רבי יוחנן. V'amar Rav v'amar Rabbi Yochanan. So here now becomes a
very nice terse little statement that gives you a sense of: how
do you define ownership or the relationship for different הלכות halachot within
this קדשים, Kodshim, like where it matters that the owner has a
different status? So here's what he says: המקדיש, hamakdish, the one who
sanctifies it, מוסיף חומש, mosif chomesh, adds a fifth. Right? The הלכה
halacha is that if you redeem a קרבן, korban, okay, and if
it got a blemish, you would add a fifth if you You
are the המקדיש, makdish, the one who sanctified. Now, normally the owner
and the one who sanctified are the same person. But let's say
I'm obligated in a קרבן, korban, I don't have money, I don't
have sheep, you're a nice guy, so you go ahead and you
sanctify your sheep and you say this sheep will be an עולה,
olah, you know for Dov's, for Dov's.
So now it's my קרבן korban in the sense it works for
me as a קרבן, korban, but you are the one who sanctified
it, you were able to, it was your sheep. So now, and
now it gets a blemish. Whose redemption has to add a fifth?
The one whose קרבן korban it is, which is me, or the
one who sanctified it, which was you because it was your sheep?
And the answer is המקדיש מוסיף חומש. Hamakdish mosif chomesh. The one
who sanctified it adds a fifth because the תורה Torah says ואם
גאל יגאל המקדיש, Ve'im gaol yigal hamakdish, if the sanctifier redeems it.
Okay, so if the sanctifier and the person whose קרבן korban it
is, it's going to work for, are different, it's only the sanctifier
who adds the fifth. המקדיש מוסיף חומש ומתכפר עושה תמורה. Hamakdish mosif
chomesh umitkapeir oseh tmurah. Now, in that same case, who would have
the ability to make a תמורה, tmurah, me or you? You sanctified
it, but it's going to function as my קרבן. korban. So there
the הלכה halacha is that the one who it atones for, okay,
he is the one that can make a תמורה, tmurah, okay? And
there's a פסוק pasuk we learn that out from. So I, if
it works for me I can make a תמורה, tmurah, but if
you're the owner, if you're the המקדיש, makdish, you add a fifth.
Okay? Making a תמורה tmurah is not necessarily a good thing because
you're not allowed to, but it means I have the power to
make a תמורה. tmurah. והתורם משלו על של חבירו טובת הנאה שלו.
Vehatoreim mishelo al shel chaveiro tovat hana'ah shelo. And if, and a
different הלכה, halacha, if I take תרומה terumah from my grain then
I'm taking it and that will exempt now your grain from being
obligated in תרומה, terumah, I'm מפריש mafrish the תרומה terumah from your
grain that you harvested and that was טבל. tevel. So the הלכה
halacha is that I now get to decide who to give that
תרומה terumah to because it was my grain I used to be
מפריש. mafrish. Anyway, the point is the following. You see that it's
only the, only if you think that the קרבן korban works for
the person, you're a מתכפר, mitkapeir, do you have the ability to
do תמורה. tmurah. So now we've got a logical problem, right? From
the fact that a מנחה mincha that is a partnership that is
owned by, that is, you know, two brothers inherited, it's not considered
that they're the owners of it, because if they were the owners
you couldn't bring a מנחה שותפות. minchat shutafut. It's their dead mother's
or dead father's מנחה. mincha. Fine. So that we've solved. It's you
don't inherit. Now, קרבן, korban, the father dies, mother dies, the two
brothers inherit. So it's not their עולה. olah. But even though it's
not their עולה, olah, one of them has the power to make
a תמורה. tmurah. That's a special category of יורש, yoreish, you know,
but two of them do not, that's like שותפות, shutafut, even though
they're not the owners. But now the גמרא Gemara is saying: But
how does that one make a תמורה tmurah if there's only one
of them? If you're, you know, if you're not an
owner then it's not going to atone for you. And if it's
not going to atone for you then you don't have the power
to make a תמורה. tmurah. So how can you say you're not
an owner and you can still make a תמורה tmurah if there's
one of you? So the גמרא Gemara has a very nice answer.
The גמרא's Gemara answer is: מקיבעא לא מכפרא מכופיא מכפרא. Mikiva lo
mechapra mikufya mechapra.
And this is a phrase that the גמרא Gemara uses in other
contexts. You do not get atonement from its fixed status, from its
basic identity, but you get it from sort of what floats on
the top. That's what literally the word means. You get it sort
of as an afterthought, as a secondary level. What does that mean?
It means if you ask whose קרבן korban this is, it's not,
it's not the heirs'. Whose קרבן korban is it? It's my mom's.
Shirley, Shirley is dead, עליה השלום. aleha hashalom. It's her קרבן. korban.
Okay? It was made to atone for her. And she's now dead.
Alright? You're still going to bring it. Okay? That's the הלכה. halacha.
If it's an עולה olah even though you don't have the owners
around you go ahead and you bring it. So she is the
one who has like the fixed identity of the function of the
קרבן korban was made to atone for her for let's say מצות
עשה. mitzvot aseh. That's קיבעא. kiva. It's fundamental function. So for me
it doesn't fun... it's not coming to work for me. Nevertheless,
after it's brought, since I like, you know, was the heir to
Shirley, after it was brought, I also, like a halo effect or
what, you know, I get some atonement from that קרבן korban because
I was the heir and I brought it even though it wasn't
my קרבן korban and therefore I get it in this sort of
like secondary level, you know, a ripple effect. Okay, so now what
do we have? I'm not the owner. Because I'm not the owner
and it's not fundamentally my קרבן, korban, if you have two brothers
they can bring a מנחה mincha that they inherited. It's not a
מנחה שותפות, minchat shutafut, it's not fundamentally theirs. But because after it's
brought it will give them some atonement, that is enough to give
them the power if there's one of them to do תמורה. tmurah.
So heirs do not own the קרבן, korban, it doesn't become their
קרבן, korban, it's not identified as their קרבן, korban, but they will
gain some atonement once it's brought, and that gives a single heir...
the power to do a תמורה. temurah. Okay, moving on. That was
a fascinating little hybrid state. Okay, איבעיא להו. ibaiylu. Now they asked
the question: קיפרו אמה שבואו או לא קיפרו. kipro ama sheba'u o
lo kipro. Now
let's say that you go ahead and you bring this עולה, olah,
right? It was this classic case we've been dealing with, which is
that it was שחטה שלא לשמה. shachata shelo lishma. And you bring
this עולה, olah, my עולה olah was שחטה שלא לשמה, shachata shelo
lishma, and it went ahead and was brought and was brought. So
we said that it's a כשר kosher קרבן, korban, but if I
had accepted a נדר neder to bring an עולה, olah, I didn't
fulfill my obligation, my נדר neder obligation. So now the גמרא Gemara
wants to know the difference between, is can we make a difference
between my obligation because I accepted a נדר neder to bring an
עולה olah and the atonement that I achieved from the קרבן? korban?
So this קרבן korban that is brought for me but was שחטה
שלא לשמה, shachata shelo lishma, so לא עלה לבעלים לשם חובה, lo
ala l'be'alim l'shem chova, and I still have to bring another קרבן
korban because of my נדר, neder, did I at least get some
atonement from this? Did it at least achieve its metaphysical function? It
didn't get me out of my legal responsibilities, but did it achieve
some metaphysical function? That's the גמרא'ס Gemara's question. איבעיא להו: ibaiylu: קיפרו
אמה שבואו או לא קיפרו?
kipro ama
sheba'u o lo kipro? Did it atone for the reason for what
it was brought or not? אמר רב ששת בריה דרב אידי: Amar
Rav Sheshet brei d'Rav Idi: מסתברא דלא קיפרו. mistavra d'lo kipro. It
makes sense to say it did not achieve any atonement for me.
דאי סלקא דעתך קיפרו, De'i salka daitach kipro, if it did achieve
atonement for me, שני למה הוא בא? sheni lama hu ba? Why
do I have to bring the second one? How do you separate
if it actually did its function and atoned for me, how do
I still have an obligation to bring a second קרבן, korban, okay?
How do you say it didn't really, but I didn't fulfill my
obligation with it? ואלא מאי, Ve'ela mai, says the גמרא, Gemara, what
do you want to say? לא קיפרו, lo kipro, that it doesn't,
it didn't achieve atonement for me and that's why I have to
bring a second קרבן korban because of my נדר neder and I
needed to achieve atonement. So if that's true, למה הוא קרב? lama
hu kareiv? Why are you bothering to bring the first one if
it's not going to achieve atonement? So it's a different way almost
or a variation of ריש לקיש'ס Reish Lakish's question, but it is
interesting that it conceptually separates between the issue of קיפרו kipro of
metaphysically atoning and about fulfilling, my you know, is it theoretically possible
that it achieves atonement and I still have an obligation to bring
the קרבן? korban? But the question, so the, that's an interesting possibility,
but the question still is, if it's not going to achieve atonement,
then why are you bringing it? And if it did achieve atonement,
then why would you have to bring the second? So let's see
what the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer is. אמר רב אשי: Amar Rav Ashi:
רב ששת בריה דרב אידי הכי קא קשיא ליה. Rav Sheshet brei
d'Rav Idi hachi ka kashya lei. No, here was the problem. אי
אמרת בשלמא לא קיפרו, Ei amart bishlama lo kipro, if you say
that it does not achieve atonement, שלא לשמו מכוח לשמו קאתי. shelo
lishmo mikoach lishmo ka'ati. I still understand why you bring it. Why
do you bring it? 'Cause it started off as a קרבן korban
that had to be brought. It started off as a totally legitimate
קרבן korban and now you sort of ruined it a little bit
that you did it שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. So it's not going
to achieve atonement and, but you can't say don't bring it. I
mean, it was already in the process of being brought and it
started off as a קרבן korban that needed to be brought. So
you made a mistake, so you finish it. You still bring it
even if it's not going to achieve atonement and that would work.
And then I'd still have to bring a second one because of
my נדר neder and I didn't get atonement. אלא אי אמרת קיפרו,
Ela ei amart kipro, but if the first one achieved atonement, why
am I bothering bringing the second קרבן? korban? Okay. So שני למה
הוא בא? sheni lama hu ba? Why is it coming? It does
not want to believe that my נדר neder could still obligate me.
If my קרבן korban atoned for me, my first one, then I
would be free from my נדר. neder. I would have done everything
I needed to do. So the גמרא'ס Gemara's basic conclusion here, which
is I think what we would have expected, but it was interesting
that it considered a division between קיפרו kipro and whether I fulfilled
my נדר. neder. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara basic seems to be
the conclusion is the first one, it's not going to achieve atonement.
You bring it because when it was sanctified, it should have been
brought. You just made a mistake and you ruined it a little
bit along the way, but obviously it was a קרבן korban that
was meant to be brought and you have to bring it. You're
not going to achieve atonement and therefore you also have to fulfill
then your נדר neder and you have to bring a makeup one.
So even though you're not going to achieve atonement, go finish bringing
it. Fine. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. איבעיא להו.
ibaiylu. Now we're going to ask a question that has nothing to
do with our special case of שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. We're going
to ask a question since we're dealing with when is atonement achieved
and some of those issues. Okay. We're going to deal with this
idea that a קרבן עולה korban olah atones for a מצות עשה,
mitzvot asei, which exact עשה asei does it work for? איבעיא להו.
ibaiylu. This is a general question about a קרבן עולה korban olah
having nothing to do with prior discussions. איבעיא להו, ibaiylu, they asked
the question: אעשה דלאחר הפרשה מכפר או לא מכפר? a'asei d'le'achar hafrasha
mechaper o lo mechaper?
I separate out an עולה olah for and it's going to work
for all my מצות עשה. mitzvot asei. I sanctify my animal and
then before I get a chance to bring it to the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, I forgot to put on תפילין tefillin today or,
you know, I ate outside of a סוכה. sukkah. Is it now
going to atone for that מצות עשה mitzvot asei that I transgressed,
didn't do, between the time it was separated and the time that
brought. Which one of those defines its identity of which sins it
works for? The act of sanctifying it or the act of bringing
it? So, that's a good question.
איבעיא להו, Ibaiya lehu, עולה olah לאחר הפרשה le-achar hafrashah? מכפרת mechaperes
או o לא lo מכפרת? mechaperes? מי אמרינן, Mi amrinan, מידי דהוי
אחטאת, midi dehavay achatatt, it should work like a חטאת. chattas. מה
חטאת דקודם הפרשה אין דלאחר הפרשה לא. Mah chattas dekodem hafrashah in
delachar hafrashah lo. A חטאת chattas only works for a sin you
did before you separated it out, not after. אף הכא נמי דקודם
הפרשה אין דלאחר הפרשה לא. Af hacha nami dekodem hafrashah in delachar
hafrashah lo. Say the same about an עולה olah for מצוות עשה.
mitzvas asei. או דלמא, O dilma, or should we say,
לא דמיא, lo damiya, it's not similar לחטאת. lechattas.
דחטאת על כל חטא וחטא בעי לאתויי חדא
חטאת.
dechattas al kol cheit vacheit ba'ei
le'asuyei chada chattas. By a חטאת, chattas, every separate sin requires a
separate חטאת. chattas. So of course it's only going to work for
the sin that I already did and then I sanctified the animal,
because a חטאת chattas has a very specific and concrete identity. So
it has to be the identity defined at the time you sanctified
and it's obviously not going to work for anything else. דחטאת על
כל חטא וחטא בעי לאתויי חדא חטאת. dechattas al kol cheit vacheit
ba'ei le'asuyei chada chattas. והכא, Vehacha, כיוון דאיכא כמה עשה גביה, keivan
de'ika kammah asei gabbeih, מכפרא, mechaperah, אעשה דלאחר הפרשה. a'asei delachar hafrashah.
So כיוון דאיכא כמה עשה גביה, keivan de'ika kammah asei gabbeih, מכפרא,
mechaperah, but by an עולה, olah, it's more generic. An
עולה olah isn't about any particular מצוות עשה. mitzvas asei. It works
for all the מצוות עשה mitzvas asei I've done. It's not linked
to a specific one. And since it's not linked to a specific
one, אעשה דלאחר הפרשה נמי מכפרא, a'asei delachar hafrashah nami mechaperah, let
it work even for ones that come afterwards. It's a very generic
type of a קרבן. korban. So that's a really good question. So
what is it? Does it define by the time of sanctifying or
by the time of being brought? תא שמע, Ta shema, come and
hear, וסמך ונרצה. vesamach venirtza.
So this is a separate דרשה drashah about the power, about the
importance of doing סמיכה. semichah. You put your hands on the קרבן
korban and then it atones for you. וכי סמיכה מכפרת? Vachi semichah
mechaperes? So the גמרא Gemara asks, the ברייתא braisa asks, is really
what's the juxtaposition that you put your hands and it atones for
you? Is it really the laying of the hands that achieves atonement?
והלא אין כפרה אלא בדם. Vehalo ein kaparah ela bedam. The כפרה
kaparah comes through the blood that's put on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. שנאמר,
shenemar, כי הדם הוא בנפש יכפר. ki hadam hu banefesh yechaper. אלא
מה
תלמוד לומר וסמך ונרצה לכפר? Ela mah talmud lomar vesamach venirtza lechaper?
So what's the
juxtaposition לכפר? lechaper? שאם עשאה לסמיכה שיורי מצוה, she'im asahah lesemichah shiyurei
mitzvah, to tell you that if you did not do the סמיכה,
semichah, you treated it like some remnant of the מצוה, mitzvah, it
doesn't really matter, I'm יוצא yotzei without it. So therefore, מעלה עליו
הכתוב כאילו לא כיפר. ma'aleh alav hakatuv ke'ilu lo kibeir. It's the
תורה Torah is going to treat it like you didn't really achieve
atonement. It's true, even without סמיכה, semichah, it'll work. But it says
וסמך ונרצה vesamach venirtza to tell you that with סמיכה, semichah, that's
when you really achieve atonement. You know, if you do everything right.
But if you leave this off and you trivialize it and say
it's not really necessary, it's going to be as if the קרבן
korban didn't really work for you. It did work for you. כאילו
לא כיפר וכיפר, Ke'ilu lo kibeir vechibeir, it did work for you,
but it was not ideal. So that's what it says. כאילו לא
כיפר וכיפר. Ke'ilu lo kibeir vechibeir. Now we would read normally, and
the גמרא Gemara is going to suggest in a minute, that that
double language means like you didn't really do it right, you only
get a C minus on your קרבן, korban, technically you still pass,
it's still a passing grade, but you didn't really do it the
way it should have been done. And to some degree we'll even
think it's as if you really didn't get atonement. If I'm forced
to admit it, I'll admit that you did. That's how we would
explain that phrase. But the גמרא Gemara reads it very differently. Rather
than saying it's like this middle state of technically you got atonement
but it wasn't great, it says you didn't get, כאילו לא כיפר,
ke'ilu lo kibeir, you didn't get atonement for something, וכיפר, vechibeir, and
you did get atonement for something else. And it's going to read
this directly into its question. So it says like this, מאי לא
כיפר? Mai lo kibeir? כאילו לא כיפר וכיפר? Ke'ilu lo kibeir vechibeir?
What does it mean you didn't get
atonement? מאי לאו, Mai lav, does it not mean דכיפר אעשה דקודם
הפרשה, dechibeir a'asei dekodem hafrashah, that the כיפר kibeir works on what
you did, all of the עשה aseis you did before you separated
it out, לא כיפר אעשה דסמיכה, lo kibeir a'asei desemichah, and the
part of the קרבן korban that didn't work,
for the fact, get this, not other עשה, aseis, that you were
מבטל mevatel the עשה asei that you did not do סמיכה semichah
on the קרבן? korban? So here's how it's reading it. Rather than
reading when you did the קרבן korban not totally right, you get
atonement but it wasn't a hundred percent, what it's reading it is
כאילו לא כיפר, ke'ilu lo kibeir, you didn't get atonement for this
one sin that you just did right now. What was this one
sin you just did right now? You didn't put your hands on
the קרבן. korban. There you didn't get atonement for. But וכיפר, vechibeir,
you got atonement for everything that preceded the time that you sanctified.
So we're going to read it that way and say the reason
you don't get atonement for not having put your hands on the
קרבן korban is because that was an עשה asei that came after
the time that you separated it. So let's take a look.
מאי לאו דכיפר אעשה דקודם הפרשה לא כיפר אעשה דסמיכה? Mai lav
dechibeir a'asei dekodem hafrashah lo kibeir a'asei desemichah? דהוי ליה Dehavay leih
And the reason you didn't get atonement for this not putting your
hands is because it came after you separated. So אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, no, עשה דסמיכה קאמרת asei de-smichah ka-amarta meaning he still read
it the same way, but he says in general I could say
the עולה olah works for sins or lack of עשה's asehs after
הפרשה. hafrashah But the one thing the עולה olah won't work for
is the sin of not having put your hands on the קרבן.
korban. Why will that not work? שאני התם דכל כמה דלא שחיט
באמר וסמוך קאי. shani hatam de-chol kamma de-lo shachit be-amor ve-smoch ka-i.
Any second before the שחיטה shchitah you have an opportunity to do
סמיכה. smichah. So you don't transgress the עשה aseh of not doing
סמיכה smichah until the moment you שחט shacht the קרבן. korban. אימת
קהוי עשה, Eimas ka-havei asei,
when have you transgressed the עשה? aseh? לאחר שחיטה, Le-achar shchitah, after
you've slaughtered it, that's the moment you transgress. לאחר שחיטה לא קמיבעי
לן, Le-achar shchitah lo kamiba'ei lan, it certainly doesn't atone for sins
you did after it was slaughtered. I just want to say it
atones for sins that you did from the time you sanctified it
until you slaughtered it. So even if I read this ברייתא braita
to say that you don't get atonement for not having done סמיכה,
smichah, that doesn't mean you don't get atonement for other things that
happened from the time you sanctified, specifically this sin occurs after the
moment of שחיטה shchitah or at the moment. Okay, so we've managed
to push off that proof. אמר ליה הונא בר יהודה לרבא, Amar
leih Huna bar Yehuda le-Rava, אימא, eima, I have a better read
of it, the way we would have read it. כיפר גברא, Kipper
gavra, what it means you atone means technically you were atoned for,
you know, your sin is forgiven, you are טהור, tahor, whatever the
case might be. But לא כיפר, lo kipper, when it says you
weren't atoned, it doesn't mean for the sin of not putting your
hands on the קרבן. korban. It
means לא כיפר כפרה שלימה, lo kipper kaparah shleimah, you didn't do
it the right way, like רש"י Rashi says, you didn't get, and
רש"י Rashi says לנחת רוח לקונו, le-nachat ruach le-kono, you didn't get
an A, God isn't so happy with you, but technically you atoned
for your sin. That's a normal way to read it and therefore
the whole case is irrelevant for our discussion. So מי לא תנן
mi lo tnan and I'll show you we say that elsewhere. והנותר
בשמן אשר על כף הכהן יתן, Ve-ha-notar ba-shemen asher al kaf ha-kohen
yitten, so this is talking about the what you do for the
נזיר, nazir, okay? And it says that the remainder you put it
on the ears or whatever and the remainder you pour on the
head. Okay, so what happens if you didn't pour the rest on
the head like you were supposed to? Similar to this idea of
סמיכה, smichah, something that is not מעכב me'akev or would not seem
to be מעכב, me'akev, it seems to be but you know it
wasn't done. How does that affect the rest of what was done?
לכפר עליו לפני ה'. Lekhapper alav lifnei Hashem. And again it's the
point that something that we on the one hand is called הנותר,
ha-notar, the remainder, and not central, it juxtaposes to this idea of
כפרה, kaparah, to atone לפני ה'. lifnei Hashem. אם נתן כיפר ואם
לא נתן לא כיפר דברי רבי עקיבא. Im natan kipper ve-im lo
natan lo kipper divrei Rabbi Akiva. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva reads
it כפשוטו ke-pshuto and he actually says yeah, the pour, even though
it's called הנותר, ha-notar, the pouring over of the oil on the
head of the נזיר, nazir, if you don't do it, it does
not work. Okay, that's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. רבי יוחנן
בן נורי אומר לא, Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri omer lo, שירי מצוה
הן, shiyarei mitzvah hen, it says הנותר, ha-notar, so they are like
a remnant of a
מצוה, mitzvah, they're not central to this working. בין ניתן בין שלא
ניתן כיפר, Bein nittan bein she-lo nittan kipper, whether you did it
on the head or you didn't pour it on the head, it
works.
ומעלין עליו כאילו לא כיפר. U-ma'alin alav ke-ilu lo kipper. But even
though it works, it's like it didn't work. So you see, we're
not talking about it works for A and it doesn't work for
B. We're saying it wasn't
great. Okay,
so מאי כאילו לא כיפר, mai ke-ilu lo kipper, what does it
mean it's as if it didn't work? אילימא דמיבעי לאתויי קרבן אחרינא,
Ilima de-mibaei le-asuye korban achrina, if it means that it really didn't
work and you have to bring another
קרבן, korban, הא אמרת בין ניתן בין לא ניתן כיפר, ha amarta
bein nittan bein lo nittan kipper, whether you did it or not,
it is מכפר. mechapper. I'm sorry, I think I've been saying נזיר,
nazir, my mistake, it's actually the case of a מצורע, metzora, my
mistake. We're talking about the טהרה taharah process of a מצורע. metzora.
Actually it was a big mistake because this is actually דווקא davka
this week's פרשה parsha of תזריע ומצורע. Tazria u-Metzora. Okay, sorry I
got confused before because whatever. Anyway, okay so we're talking about the
טהרה taharah process of a מצורע metzora and part of that process
is you put the oil on the head. Okay, and רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says because it's juxtaposed to the word וכיפר, ve-chipper, therefore
without that it doesn't work. But רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri says it's this middle thing, כאילו לא כיפר וכיפר. ke-ilu
lo kipper ve-chipper. So the גמרא Gemara says, what do you mean
by this?
אילימא דמיבעי לאתויי קרבן אחרינא, Ilima de-mibaei le-asuye korban achrina, if you
literally mean לא כיפר lo kipper and we have to bring another
קרבן korban for the מצורע, metzora, so הא אמרת בין ניתן בין
לא ניתן כיפר, ha amarta bein nittan bein lo nittan kipper, but
no you explicitly said that it really does work. אלא כיפר גברא
לא כיפר כפרה שלימה. Ella kipper gavra lo kipper kaparah shleimah. What
it means is technically the מצורע metzora is טהור, tahor, he can
get on with his life, but the מצוה mitzvah wasn't done the
way it was supposed to have been done. הכא נמי כיפר כיפר
וכו' Hacha nami kipper kipper etc. say the same thing here. So
basically why are you getting yourself worked up to think that this
idea of לא כיפר lo kipper means you one particular מצוה mitzvah
wasn't done properly, right the מצוה mitzvah of you know putting the
hands on, and that gave you this whole question about does it
work for things that לאחר le'achar הפרשה? hafrashah. No, לא כיפר lo
kipper means the whole thing was a you got a C-minus on
it. Okay, but it doesn't mean there's a particular thing that it
doesn't work for. So the גמרא... Gemara... The גמרא Gemara says, you
know why? I'm not convinced, because there too I could say it
means it works for A and it doesn't work for B. What
would that be? התם נמי, Hasam nami, כיפר במתנות לא כיפר במתנות
הראש. kiper b'matanos lo kiper b'matanos harosh. No, I can make the
split there too. I could say that the same way I said
by the סמיכה, smicha, it works for your prior sins, it does
not work for the sin of not putting the hands on it,
so it's not 50/50, it's not you got a C minus, this
was a hundred percent, this was zero. Here too, I will say
by the case of the מצורע, metzora, it's not that you got
a C minus, it's that it works what you did by putting
the by putting the oil on the ear, okay, that worked. And
that was the כיפר. kiper. What didn't work was the מצוה mitzvah
of putting the oil on the head. So it's so כיפר ולא
כיפר kiper v'lo kiper means part A you did correct, part B
you did not do correct. Does that mean you have to redo
part B? That's a debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafos. Okay.
תא שמע. Ta shema. So now we're going to try again. רבי
שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, כבשי עצרת למה הן באין? kivsei atzeres
lamah hen ba'in? Why do you bring the lambs on שבועות Shavuos
with the bread? So the גמרא Gemara says למה הן באין? lamah
hen ba'in? כבשי עצרת שלמים נינהו. kivsei atzeres shlamim ninhu. So what
do you mean למה הן באין? lamah hen ba'in? They're כבשי עצרת
kivsei atzeres are שלמים. shlamim. So so what? But the point is
we're going to see in a minute that the answer is going
to connect it to טומאת מקדש. tumas mikdash. And we know that
שלמים shlamim have no relationship to טומאת מקדש. tumas mikdash. טומאת מקדש
tumas mikdash is connected to a חטאת. chatas. So clearly before we
can get to the answer of טומאת מקדש, tumas mikdash, the גמרא
Gemara is saying that you must have made like there must be
some mistake here. You can't be talking about the שלמים shlamim that
you bring on שבועות. Shavuos. אלא Ella says the גמרא Gemara fine.
שעירי עצרת למה הן באין? se'irei atzeres lamah hen ba'in? How about
the fact that you bring two שעירי לחטאת se'irei l'chatas on שבועות?
Shavuos? Why do you need two? על טומאת מקדש וקדשיו, Al tumas
mikdash v'kodashav, for the טומאה tumah of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
that's a standard reason why you bring a חטאת ציבור. chatas tzibbur.
Okay so why do you so then the question is why do
you need two? נזרק דמו של ראשון שניה למה קריב? Nizrak damo
shel rishon shniyah lamah kareiv? Once you sprinkle the blood of the
first one why are you bothering to bring the second one? So
the answer is רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon's answer is על טומאה שאירע
בין זה לזה. al tumah she'eira bein zeh l'zeh. In some type
of a טומאה tumah occurred between the bringing of the first one
and the second one, it covers the gap of the ten minutes
between the two קרבנות. korbanos. So of course that's crazy because if
that's true you have to worry every few minutes, you should have
to bring a קרבן korban every few minutes, which is what רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says. אם כן מעתה Im kein me'atah said רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon from here you see ראויין היו ישראל להקריב קרבנותיהן
בכל עת ובכל שעה. re'uyin hayu Yisrael l'hakriv korbanoseihen bechol eis uvechol
sha'ah. We really should be so careful about our sense of טומאה
tumah and so on and that you know and an unwitting טומאת
המקדש tumas HaMikdash that we should have to bring a קרבן korban
every minute, we have to even worry here about the two minutes
between the two
קרבנות. korbanos. אלא שחסך הכתוב, Ella shechasak haksav, but the תורה Torah
had רחמנות rachmanus on us and didn't want us to be spending
all of our money and gave us a little bit of a
breather and says you know we won't get punished from one יום
טוב Yom Tov to the next, from bringing one קרבן חטאת korban
chatas to the next, it'll cover all of the טומאות מקדש tumos
mikdash between you know one יום טוב Yom Tov and the next,
or one ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh or whatever the case is. But
but
here in this one place on שבועות Shavuos it sort of wants
to get across this message, so it requires us two קרבנות korbanos
to cover any טומאה tumah that occurs between קרבן korban one and
קרבן korban two. Okay but now we have actually some evidence for
our proof because this actually works like an עשה. aseh. Why does
it work like an עשה? aseh? טומאת מקדש Tumas mikdash is a
לא תעשה. lo sa'aseh. רש"י Rashi says there's also an עשה, aseh,
okay but still I think the bigger point is is that טומאת
מקדש tumas mikdash is like generic, it's not like a חטאת, chatas,
it's not like a particular sin. And since it's not linked to
a particular sin, it's generic, it has the ability potentially to work
on sins after הפרשה. hafrasha. Okay and that's what we're going to
say, that's what seems to be here. You separated out your two
שעירי לחטאת se'irei l'chatas on שבועות Shavuos and then you brought one
and then the second one is coming for any טומאה tumah that
occurred between. Okay but that's טומאה tumah that occurred after it had
been sanctified. So you see that if something has like this generic
quality it works even for sins that occur after it was sanctified.
All right?
So let's take a look. והכא דעשה לאחר הפרשה, V'hacha d'aseh l'achar
hafrasha, it's an עשה, aseh, I think it more like means analogous
to an עשה aseh after הפרשה hafrasha וקא מכפר v'ka mechaper
and it atones. So you see that it works because it worked
for the טומאה tumah after it was sanctified. So the גמרא Gemara
says אי דאפרשינהו בבת אחת הכי נמי. ee d'afrishinhu b'vas achas hachi
nami. You know what? If you sanctified them at the same time
you'd have a good proof because then it works for טומאה tumah
the second one works for טומאה tumah that occurred after the act
of sanctification. הכא במאי עסקינן דאפרשינהו בזה אחר זה. Hacha b'mai askinan
d'afrishinhu bezeh achar zeh. No. Where we're talking about is the reason
you need two is the following scenario: You sanctified one and you
brought it and then you waited ten minutes, you sanctified the other
one and you brought that. And that's covering the sins between the
two. But the sanctity of the second one occurred only after the
first one was brought and that's how it can work on the
טומאה tumah that occurred after the first one. So the גמרא Gemara
says one minute, but the פסוק pasuk just says you always bring
two. It doesn't say you bring two in this way and make
sure to sanctify the second one. than after the first one. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says, וליכא ולימא ליה לקרא דכי כתיבא בזכר
זה כתיבא? v'laika uleimalay lekra d'chi k'siva b'zecher zeh k'siva? You're going
to go and say the פסוקים psukim are only talking about that
case? That's the only scenario that you bring two קרבנות korbanot is
that you sanctified it after? But if you sanctified them at the
same time there's no purpose in bringing the first one because it
can't work for טומאה tumah afterwards? No. It seems like the תורה
Torah is talking that you can sanctify them both at the same
time and the second one still works for טומאה tumah after the
first one. So you see that it can work for things that
come... if it's generic, it can work for things that come after
the time of הקדשה. hakdasha. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, רב
פפא Rav Pappa says, that seems to be a pretty darn good
proof. But רב פפא Rav Pappa says no, there's another reason you
cannot sort of generalize from that. קרבנות ציבור קאמרת? Korbanos tzibur ka'amart?
You want to talk about a קרבן ציבור? korban tzibur? שאני קרבנות
ציבור דלאי בית דין מתנה עליהם. Shani korbanos tzibur d'lae beis din
masneh aleihem. A קרבן ציבור korban tzibur which is brought by communal
funds, בית דין, beis din, like the rabbis, can sort of stipulate
and say we're always in control. And under some... if certain conditions
will happen in the future, we retroactively are saying that we sort
of never sanctified it, you know, for that purpose. So here too,
even if you sanctify them both at the same time, what the
בית דין beis din would sort of implicitly be saying is, since
we need that second one to work for טומאה tumah after the
first one, even if you sanctify it at the same time, we're
going to say that the sanctity of the second one doesn't take
effect until right before it's brought, and therefore it can cover any
טומאה tumah between the first and the second. So because בית דין
beis din gets to like write the rules and say when this
thing how הקדש hekdesh takes effect in these cases of קרבנות ציבור,
korbanos tzibur, we can always say that the second one works on
the טומאות tumas between the two because the sanctity only began right
before it was brought. Okay, because of בית דין's beis din ability.
כי רב יהודה, Ki Rav Yehuda, like what רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
says. דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, D'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, קרבנות
ציבור סכין משחטן למה שהן. korbanos tzibur sachin meshachtan l'ma shehein. A
קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur,
the way you... whatever you slaughtered, that sort of defines its identity.
This is like a complicated issue about... I don't want to go
into the specifics about like if you have a leftover תמיד tamid
and then you slaughter it, it becomes an עולה olah for קיץ
המזבח, keitz hamizbei'ach, a sort of an עולה olah to keep the
מזבח mizbei'ach busy. But the point is, because it's a קרבן ציבור,
korban tzibur, we can sort of stipulate under these conditions it'll change
its identity. It'll be like it was never sanctified for this, it
was sanctified for something else, and that's how it's going to work.
So here too, it's a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, we can make
it like it was sanctified later, and you can't prove that it
works on things that happened after it was sanctified. Okay. So... קרבנות
ציבור סכין משחטן למה שהן. korbanos tzibur sachin meshachtan l'ma shehein. אמר
ליה רב יוסף בריה דרב שמואל לרב פפא, Amar lei Rav Yosef
brei d'Rav Shmuel l'Rav Pappa, ומי סבירא ליה לרבי שמעון לאי בית
דין מתנה עליהן? Umi sevira lei l'Rabbi Shimon lae beis din masneh
aleihen? Can you really say that רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, because רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon was the one who made the point that the
two sacrifices for שבועות, Shavuos, the second one covers the טומאה tumah
after the first one. Can you really say that רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon holds of this לאי בית דין מתנה עליהם lae beis din
masneh aleihem to get out of the proof that I'm bringing that
it works for sins after it was sanctified? דאמר רב אידי בר
אבין אמר רב עמרם אמר רב יצחק אמר רב יוחנן, D'amar Rav
Idi bar Avin amar Rav Amram amar Rav Yitzchak amar Rav Yochanan,
תמידין שלא הוצרכו לציבור, temidin shelo hutzrechu l'tzibur, if you have this,
you have a קרבן תמיד korban tamid that was brought with the
old funds and now it's a new year, it's after ניסן, Nissan,
and you're not allowed to bring this קרבן תמיד korban tamid because
it was brought with the old funds, do you have... do you
have to wait until it gets a blemish in order to redeem
it? So... so the teaching is, לדברי רבי שמעון אין נפדין תמימים.
l'divrei Rabbi Shimon ein nifdin temimim. For רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon you
cannot redeem it without a blemish. It's normal sanctity, and before you
redeem it in order to then let you buy it with the
new funds, so it'll be a קרבן korban brought this year with
the moneys collected this year, you have to wait until it gets
a blemish like any normal הלכה halacha by when can you redeem
a
קרבן? korban? אבל לדברי חכמים נפדין תמימים. Aval l'divrei chachamim nifdin temimim.
But the חכמים chachamim say you can redeem it without a blemish.
How so? Can you redeem something without a blemish? So the answer
is, because it's a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur and בית דין beis
din gets to make up the rules, we can basically say that
it was... in these circumstances we never meant to sanctify it in
the first first place, and therefore it can be redeemed without a
blemish. The point though being that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon doesn't allow
that. And if רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it has to follow
the normal rules, and we don't get to say "Oh, in this
case it was never sanctified," you see רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon does
not hold that לאי בית דין מתנה עליהם. lae beis din masneh
aleihem. And therefore we're back to the point that the קרבנות korbanot
by שבועות, Shavuos, they were sanctified both at the beginning and nevertheless
the second one works for טומאה tumah that occurred
after. ועוד, V'od, and in addition, you know, so we're going to
stop with here and we will just wrap this whole thing up
tomorrow. But the basic point is, it's a great question: do these
generic קרבנות, korbanot, the עשה aseh or the חטאת chatas that works
not in general, that's very concrete, but the חטאת chatas that works
for טומאת מקדש, tumas mikdash, does it work for things after it
was sanctified? And just like we had some cases about if you
didn't do סמיכה, semicha, if you didn't do the oil on the
top of the מצורע, metzora, that it sort of said לא כיפר
ולא כיפר lo kiper v'lo kiper where the simple meaning there was
it didn't work 100 percent, you know, or the way the גמרא
Gemara sort of says it, you got a C minus or whatever,
you were atoned for but you didn't make God
happy. It worked for what occurred before, but it didn't work for
this particular problem. It didn't work for the lack of doing סמיכה.
smicha. It didn't work for the fact that you didn't do the
pouring on the oil on the head properly.
And that was its attempt to prove that things don't
work to atone for after it was sanctified. So it's a strange
read of that case. That's what the גמרא Gemara tried to say.
Anyway, at the end of the day, the simpler way to read
that is it just means you got a C minus but you
still passed. And that actually if we use the example of the
חטאת chatas here for טומאת מקדש tumas mikdash and the whole thing
about the two animals and the טומאה tuma between them, we'll come
to the conclusion if we read it without the special idea that
בית דין Beis Din manipulated it, that actually an עולה olah can
work for עשין aseis after it was sanctified and a חטאת chatas
of ציבור tzibur can work for טומאת מקדש tumas mikdash for after
it was sanctified. So we'll wrap this up.